Guide to the Papers of Mordecai Sheftall (1735-1797), undated, 1761-1867, 1873, 1932, 1941 (bulk 1777-1778) *P-12
American Jewish Historical Society, Newton Centre, MA and New York, NY
Francis Sheftall (Binder 1) (See also Reel 12)
Benjamin Sheftall (Binder 1)
Sheftall Family (Binder 1)
Hetty(Binder 1)
Works Progress Administration Guide (Box 14)
Works Progress Administration Index Folders (Box 18)
Reel 2
Newspapers - Oversized Folder 1 (OS2F)
Reel 3
Works Progress Administration Index Cards (Box 17)
1st Regiment/1st Battalion #1-134 (Binder 5)
2nd Regiment/2nd Battalion #1-200 (Binder 5)
Reel 4
2nd Regiment/2nd Battalion #201-295 (Binder 5)
3rd Regiment/3rd Battalion #1-328 (Binder 6)
Reel 5
4th Battalion/4th Regiment #1-239 (Binder 7)
Signed-Only, Illegible, and Fragmented Provision Returns #1A-187 (Binder 8)
Reel 6
Signed-Only, Illegible, and Fragmented Provision Returns #188-363 (Binder 8)
South Carolina Regiments, Battalions and Units #1-35 (Binder 9)
Multiple Battalions or Regiments #1-8 (Binder 9)
Artificers #1-33 (Binder 9)
Artillery #1-212 (Binder 9)
Reel 7
Barrack Master #1-22 (Binder 9)
Cattle Guard and Drovers #1-32 (Binder 9)
Coopers #1-2 (Binder 9)
Grenadiers #1-16 (Binder 9)
Independent Companies, Militias, and Volunteers 1-35 (Binder 9)
Light Dragoons/Light Infantry #1-125 (Binder 10)
Reel 8
Light Dragoons/Light Infantry #126-291 (Binder 10)
Reel 9
Magazine/Main Guard #1-148 (Binder 10)
Sick and Hospital #1-137 (Binder 11)
Reel 10
Sick and Hospital #138-259 (Binder 11)
Wagoners #1-87 (Binder 11)
Reel 11
Wagoners #88-181 (Binder 11)
Wagoners of South Carolina #1-32 (Binder 11)
Bulloch Galley #1-16 (Binder 12)
Congress Galley #1-37 (Binder 12)
Washington Galley #1-19 (Binder 12)
Washington,Congress,Lee,Bulloch Gallies 1-12 (Binder 12)
Other Boats including the Lee Galley #1-45 (Binder 12)
Reel 12
Unknown Vessels #1-23 (Binder 12)
American Revolution Account Books and Ledgers #1-25 (Binder 13)
American Revolution Individual Ledger Pages #1-11 (Binder 4)
Provision Return Unit Covers #1-18 (Binder 4)
American Revolution Provision Return and Other Correspondence #1-27 (Binder 4)
War Credentials and Case Against United States and Georgia Records #1A-11 (Binder 4)
Invoice to Mary Hartley from Mrs. Sheftall for Sewing and Gowns, [Christmas Day], 1778 (Binder 1)
Access Restrictions
The collection is closed to the public. Documents may be viewed by microfilm or through the digital collections of the Center for Jewish History. The original documents may be viewed only by special permission of the Director of Library and Archives.
Container List
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Subgroup I: Mordecai Sheftall, Sheftall Family Papers, and Privateer Papers, undated, 1761-1867, 1932
  This subgroup contains personal papers relating to several Sheftall family members. Items in Subgroup I include documents from Mordecai Sheftall, his wife, Frances, and their sons, Sheftall, Moses and Benjamin. Documents include correspondence, bills of sale for items, land, and slaves; business agreements, prisoner parole documents, merchant and account receipt books, newspaper clippings, naturalization certificates, the last will and testament of Mordecai Sheftall (from 1778), and a listing of his property at his death.
  Some of the documents in this Subgroup are closely linked to material in Subgroup II: American Revolutionary and Continental Troop Commissarial Work and Provision Return Records, Series I: American-Revolution Correspondence, War Credentials and Documentation and should be used in conjunction with that Subgroup and Series.
  - Series I: Mordecai Sheftall Papers, undated, 1761-1795, 1932
    This series consists of two subseries of documents related primarily to the business dealings of Mordecai Sheftall, his imprisonment during the American Revolution, his business affairs after the Revolution, his Last Will and Testament, and a listing of household items, presumably at his death. Also included is one ledger and one account book dating during the years of 1761-1795 with a time gap between the years of 1776-1790. One ledger and one account book dating during the years of 1761-1795 with a time gap between the years of 1776-1790 are also within this series.
    Some of the documents in this Series are closely linked to material in Subgroup II: American Revolutionary and Continental Troop Commissarial Work and Provision Return Records, Series I: American-Revolution Correspondence, War Credentials and Documentation and should be used in conjunction with that Subgroup and Series.
    - Subseries I: Mordecai Sheftall Correspondence and Papers, undated, 1770, 1772, 1777, 1778-1782, 1784, 1786, 1788-1792, 1794, 1932; Binder 1, Items 1-39.
      Arranged chronologically.
      Because Quartermasters and Issues Commissaries purchased items from their personal monetary accounts and then charged purchased supplies to the Continental Congress on contract, it was difficult at times to readily distinguish between correspondence of a personal business nature and that of the business of the Continental Congress and Troops in respect to certain items in the collection. Therefore, several of the letters not initially transcribed and indexed by the WPA were placed either in this subseries of personal papers or Subgroup II: American Revolutionary and Continental Troop Commissarial Work and Provision Return Records, Series I: Revolution Correspondence, War Credentials and Documentation. The two areas should therefore be used together in deciphering Mordecai Sheftall's American Revolution and private merchant business dealings.
      This personal papers Subseries contains material primarily on Mordecai's business dealings pre- and post-American Revolution, his parole after his imprisonment by the British forces, and his appointment as the agent for the State of Georgia to purchase clothing for the militia. One of the few personal letters in this Subseries is from Mordecai to his wife, Frances. Mordecai was still a prisoner, albeit on parole, in Sunbury, Georgia, while Frances was exiled from Savannah to Charleston, South Carolina during April 1779. Mordecai expresses his pleasure at hearing from her in a letter of February 26. He writes that he was released to Sunbury from the British prison ship Nancy on Feburary 25th, while his son, Sheftall, remained on the vessel. He writes that his "friends from Savannah" will make Sheftall Sheftall's life as comfortable as possible, as circumstances will permit. He expresses his love for his wife and children and asks that Frances give blessings and compliments to both his children and his friends (Item #13). A letter to Sheftall Sheftall aboard the Nancy from his father Mordecai (Item #14) also appears in this Subseries dated April 9, 1779. Mordecai urges his son to have patience in regards to his confinement, offering him hope that he would soon be paroled as a prisoner exchange is to take place, and expresses his approval of Sheftall writing to his mother. These two letters are the only two appearing in the collection on a personal basis from the time period of Mordecai and Sheftall Sheftall's imprisonment by the British either in Sunbury, on the Nancy or for their time on the island of Antigua.
      Several letters regarding Sheftall and supplies are located in this series. Item #17, dated May 24, 1781, bestows on Mordecai bills of exchange in the amount of $4,200 from the Continental Congress in Philadelphia. This credit memo was to be used to procure clothing for the militias from the French, giving Sheftall the power to procure items as the Agent on behalf of the State of Georgia. Two letters, dated September 25, 1781 and April 16, 1782 follow from Philadelphia requesting an accounting of the state of monies and procurement of items for the militias.
      Item #32, dated 1791, sees the start of Mordecai's inquiry to John Wereat requesting reimbursement from the government in recovering funds expended during the American Revolution. Unfortunately by this year, the time period to petition the new government for monetary compensation had passed, though the governmental coffers to reimburse were also depleted. Sheftall sets out his monetary claims in Items #35-36 and includes his written petition to Congress in Item #37. Item #38 is the last personal letter in the collection written by Mordecai to his son, Sheftall on April 25, 1792.
      - (Binder 1)
        - Appraisal of Property List, undated; WPA_G-0317; Indexed #326 (Item 1)
        - R. Judah to [Mordecai?] Sheftall, undated; WPA_G-0329; Indexed #328 (Item 2)
        - [John?] Stewart, Letter to Mordecai Sheftall at Mt. Raven…Reporting Indian Raids, October 8, [1770?]; WPA_H-0010; Indexed #252 (Item 3)
        - Partnership Agreement Between Mordecai Sheftall and John Brunson on Breeding Cattle, September 15, 1772; WPA_H-0007; Indexed #253 (Item 4)
        - Rich[ard] Eastmad, Cattle Drover, and Brothers Hall to Mordecai Sheftall on Meeting Florida Scout Sam [More Leanton] and Other Matters, October 17, 1777; WPA_G-0324; Indexed #255 (Item 5)
        - Last will and testament of Mordecai Sheftall, 1778; WPA_H-0005; Indexed #257 (Item 6)
        - J.B. Girardeau to Mordecai Sheftall, May 5, 1778; WPA_B-0283; Indexed #258 (Item 7)
        - Receipt Bill from John Burke to Mesr. Sheftall for Room and Board and Horses, November 26-December 1, 1778; WPA_B-0276; Indexed #259 (Item 8)
        - Invoice from Lestarjette & Co. for Fourteen Yards of "Cloudid Silk", December 14, 1778; WPA_B-0274; Indexed #260 (Item 9)
        - Prisoner's Parole, [1779]; WPA_B-0281; Indexed #266 (Item 10)
        - Prisoner's Parole to Remain in Sunbury Under the Orders of Major Drummond, Commanding Officer, 1779; WPA_B-0282; Indexed #265 (Item 11)
        - William Jones, Savannah, to Mordecai Sheftall on Board Ship Nancy, Regarding Shipment of Rum and Sugar, March 9, 1779; WPA_H-0011; Indexed #261 (Item 12)
        - Mordecai Sheftall, Sunbury, GA, Letter to His Wife, Frances Sheftall, [Charleston, SC], April 6, 1779; WPA_H-0029; Indexed #263 (Item 13)
        - Mordecai Sheftall, Sunbury, GA, Letter to Sheftall Sheftall, On Board the Prison Ship Nancy, April 9, 1779; WPA_H-0046; Indexed #264 (Item 14)
        - Resolve of Congress, Respecting a Charge for the Brigantine Hinchinbrook and Supplies to Militia, by Mordecai Sheftall, September 14, 1780; WPA_H-0016; Indexed #267 (Item 15)
        - Joseph Wood, Port "Royall" to Mordecai Sheftall, Philadelphia, January 20, 1781; WPA_B-0278; Indexed #269 (Item 16)
        - George Walton, W[illiam] Few, Richard How[e]ly, Philadelphia, Instructions to Mordecai Sheftall, Philadelphia, "Public Service," regarding use of money from French loan for purchase of clothing for Georgia militia, May 24, 1781; WPA_H-0019; Indexed #271 (Item 17)
        - George Walton and Edward Telfair to Mordecai Sheftall, September 25, 1781; WPA_H-0002; Indexed #272 (Item 18)
        - Autograph Cover for Correspondence (Item #18), "Gift of A.S.W. Rosenbach, Feb. 1932 from the Collection of Mrs. Walter M. Brickner", February 1932 (Item 19)
        - Edward Telfair to Mordecai Sheftall, April 16, 1782; WPA_H-0049; Indexed #273 (Item 20)
        - Autograph Cover for Correspondence, "Gift of A.S.W. Rosenbach, Feb. 1932 from the Collection of Mrs. Walter M. Brickner", February 1932 (Item 21)
        - Mordecai Sheftall and Samuel Elbert Agreement for Purchase of Parcel of Land, June 21, 1784; WPA_H-0013; Indexed #274 (Item 22)
        - Nathan Bush, Augusta, GA to Mordecai Sheftall, Esq., Commissary General of Issues, Savannah, GA, Favored by J[ohn] Jones, November 12, 1784; WPA_C-0001; Indexed #275 (Item 23)
        - Mordecai Sheftall, Savannah, GA, Letter to Sheftall Sheftall, Augusta, February 28, 1786; WPA_H-0043; Indexed #277 (Item 24)
        - Andrew Maybank to Mordecai Sheftall, June 14, 1786; WPA_B-0279; Indexed #279 (Item 25)
        - Col. William MacIntosh to Mordecai Sheftall, Savannah, GA, August 10, 1786; WPA_B-0277; Indexed #280 (Item 26)
        - Description and Price of Item 28, with Incorrect Date of Letter Printed, undated (Item 27)
        - William O'Bryen; Warrant to Confess Judgment to Levi Sheftall, Witnessed by Mordecai Sheftall, January 1, 1788 (Item 28)
        - John Wereat, Mt. Hope, GA, Letter to Mordecai Sheftall, Savannah on Clothe for Ethiopians (Slaves) and Potential Sheftall Visit, December 2, 1788; WPA_H-0020; Indexed #282 (Item 29)
        - J. Gunn, New York, NY, Letter to Mordecai Sheftall, Savannah, GA, June 22, 1789; WPA_H-0032; Indexed #283 (Item 30)
        - Thomas P. Carnes, Attorney General of Georgia, letter to [Mordecai Sheftall?] Requesting Receipts of Persons who Received Cash Obtained from Philadelphia, April 20, 1790; WPA_G-0327; Indexed #284 (Item 31)
        - John Wereat, Philadelphia, letter to Mordecai Sheftall, Esq., Savannah, by Georgia Packet; Capt. Burrows Advising Submission of Claim in Petition to Legislature, July 16, 1791; WPA_G-0330; Indexed #285 (Item 32)
        - Agreement Whereby Mordecai Sheftall is to Settle Dispute Between Andrew Harris and Abraham Delyon, September 14, 1791; WPA_G-0325; Indexed #287 (Item 33)
        - John Milton, Augusta, GA, to Mordecai Sheftall, Savannah, GA, Regarding Transcription of Resolutions of Georgia House of Assembly, September 28, 1791; WPA_G-0235; Indexed #288 (Item 34)
        - Mordecai Sheftall's Sworn Statement of Personal Losses Suffered by Him as Deputy Commissary General of Issues at Time Savannah was Captured (1 of 2), January 12, 1792; WPA_ G-0374-A; Indexed #290 (Item 35)
        - Mordecai Sheftall's Sworn Statement of Personal Losses Suffered by Him as Deputy Commissary General of Issues at Time Savannah was Captured (2 of 2), January 12, 1792; WPA_G-0374-B; Indexed #290 (Item 36)
        - Mordecai Sheftall Petition to Congress for Settlement of Account, January 12, 1792; WPA_H-0030; Indexed # 289 (Item 37)
        - Mordecai Sheftall to Sheftall Sheftall, April 25, 1792; WPA_G-0323; Indexed #294 (Item 38)
        - Executors of Samuel Elbert vs. Mordecai Sheftall, Petition for Foreclosure, August 1, 1794; WPA_H-0036; Indexed #298 (Item 39)
    - Subseries II: Mordecai Sheftall Ledgers and Account Book, 1761-1774, 1783, 1788, 1790-1795; Binders 2 and 3.
      This portion of the collection contains two items. The first document is a multi-page, pocket-sized and leather-bound account ledger/receipt book dated August 1761 to June 1774. This ledger contains 250 pages of customer account and payment transactions conducted with Sheftall, and signed by those he did business with. This is an excellent document highlighting the inhabitants of Savannah, the items and materials purchased through Sheftall, and his accounting of their account payments. This item was donated to the American Jewish Historical Society by A.S.W. Rosenbach in honor of his mother, Isabella. The second item in this Subseries is Mordecai's mercantile ledger, started in 1783, with entries for 1788, but primarily through 1790-1795. While this document does not contain as many pages as the first item, its 88 pages of entries deal primarily with Mordecai's accounts with pre- and post-Revolutionary merchant ships.
      - (Binder 2)
        - Mordecai Sheftall Account Ledger, 1761-1774 (Item 2)
      - (Binder 3)
        - Mordecai Sheftall Mercantile Ledger, 1783, 1788, 1790-1795; WPA_B-0419; Indexed #166-193 (Item 3)
  - Series II: Sheftall Family Papers, undated, 1780-1867
    This portion of the collection contains those pieces of correspondence and other document types regarding members of the Sheftall family including Mordecai Sheftall's wife, Frances, and their sons, Sheftall, Moses and Benjamin. Documents regarding general family members are found here as well. Several items in Series V: General Family Papers are unidentifiable as to which specific family member they originate from, and were therefore housed together under General Family Papers. Documents in Series V should also be used in conjunction with Subgroup II: American Revolutionary and Continental Troop Commissarial Work and Provision Return Records, Series I: American-Revolution Correspondence, War Credentials and Documentation.
    - Subseries I: Sheftall Sheftall, undated, 1780-1781, 1787, 1792, 1799, 1817, 1840; Binder 1, Items 1-17.
      This portion of the collection contains correspondence of Sheftall Sheftall, including his instructions from the War Department for the packet ship Carolina from 1780 and a subsequent letter from 1781 demanding that the Carolina be allowed to obtain water onshore. Other letters include several items of personal correspondence with Sheftall's father, Mordecai, relating the wedding of his brother, Moses, information regarding Mordecai's claims against the United States, and other personal and business matters from 1792.
      A letter from Mordecai to Sheftall aboard the British prison ship Nancy dated April 9, 1778 may be found in Subgroup I, Series I, Subseries I(Item #14). Items 12-15 in this Subseries are letters detailing the capture of William Brown, accused of stealing a horse and a Negro boy from their owner, Ebenezer Jackson. Two 19thcentury letters are included in this Subseries to Sheftall, one an inquiry on purchasing a tract of land from Sheftall in 1817. The final piece of correspondence in this subseries is from James C. Pope dating from 1840. Pope writes to Sheftall by request of friends in London on behalf of English relatives of Abraham de Paiba, and asks Sheftall if he has any information regarding de Paiba and his whereabouts.
      - (Binder 1)
        - Affidavit Draft by the Son of Mordecai Sheftall [Sheftall Sheftall?] Attesting to Mordecai's Commissionary of Issues Service and Sheftall's Position as Deputy Commissionary of Issues from July 1777-December 1778, not signed, undated; WPA_G-0234; Indexed #325 (Item 1)
        - War Office Instructions from Richard Pe[ters] to Sheftall Sheftall, Flag Master of the Sloop Carolina Packett, December 19, 1780; WPA_H-0047; Indexed #268 (Item 2)
        - Sheftall Sheftall, Flag Master on the Sloop Carolina Under a Flag of Truce, to the Commanding Officer of Fort Arbuthnot [Fort Moultrie] Making Additional Request to Fill Water Casks, March 9, 1781; WPA_F-0445; Indexed #270 (Item 3)
        - Note Regarding Item Added to Original Collection, Letter, J. Gunn to Sheftall, Sheftall, N.Y. (Item 4)
        - J. Gunn (New York, NY) to Sheftall Sheftall (Savannah, GA), July 5, 1787 (Item 5)
        - Lachlan McIntosh, Savannah, GA., Letter to Sheftall Sheftall, Philadelphia, PA, March 9, 1792; WPA_H-0025; Indexed #291 (Item 6)
        - Sheftall Sheftall, Philadelphia, PA, Letter to Mordecai Sheftall, Savannah, GA, March 30, 1792; WPA_H-0023; Indexed #292 (Item 7)
        - Sheftall Sheftall, Philadelphia, letter to Mordecai Sheftall, Savannah Regarding Submission of Claim to Secretary [Alexander] Hamilton (Note: End of letter mentions, "This is Erev Passover, my small gutts is warring with the Big One), April 6, 1792; WPA_G-0328; Indexed #293 (Item 8)
        - Sheftall Sheftall, Philadelphia, PA, Letter to Mordecai Sheftall, Savannah, GA, July 8, 1792; WPA_H-0042; Indexed #295 (Item 9)
        - Sheftall Sheftall to Mordecai Sheftall (Pages 1 and 2), November 30, 1792; WPA_H-0014-1; Indexed #296 (Item 10)
        - Sheftall Sheftall to Mordecai Sheftall (Pages 3 and 4), November 30, 1792; WPA_H-0014-2; Indexed #296 (Item 11)
        - William Brown Regarding Horse and Slave Theft William Brown, May 1799; WPA_E-0205; Indexed #303 (Item 12)
        - Robert Tanner to Mr. Wm. Williams Regarding Horse and Slave Theft, William Brown; Verso Has Unidentified Map of Possible Fortification, "Edwards land" (1 of 4), May 1, 1779; WPA_E-0204; Indexed #300 (Item 13)
        - Affidavit of Robert Tanner on the Character of the Men who Captured Alleged Thief, William Brown, May 2, 1779; WPA_G-0326; Indexed #301 (Item 14)
        - Note from S. Sheftall regarding "packet and papers in it, belongs to William Brown, now in jail for stealing a negroe boy, and a horse the property of Ebenezer Jackson", May 29, 1799; WPA_G-0321; Indexed #302 (Item 15)
        - Ransom Swinney, Eatonton, Putnam County [GA], Letter to S. Sheftall, Savannah, GA, Regarding Potential Purchase of Sheftall Property, August 23, 1817; WPA_H-0006; Indexed #305 (Item 16)
        - James S. Pope, Charleston, SC, Letter to Sheftall Sheftall, January 25, 1840; WPA_H-0039; Indexed #311 (Item 17)
    - Subseries II: Moses Sheftall, undated, 1795, 1807, 1815, 1827, 1833-1834; Binder 1, Items 1-10 and OS2 item.
      The eleven items in Moses Sheftall subseries are correspondence, bills of sale for property, a receipt for carpeting, and the Federal Union newspaper from Milledgeville, Georgia dated June 20, 1833 and located in Oversized Material. Two of the documents are notes regarding items in the collection [Item #3 and #5].
      - (Binder 1)
        - [A. Clinton? Or A. Carter?] to Dr [Moses?] Sheftall Regarding Jewish and Christian Attitudes Toward Miracles, March 23, undated; WPA_E-0203; Indexed #323 (Item 1)
        - Abraham Baldwin, Philadelphia to Dr. Moses Sheftall, Savannah, GA, March 3, 1795; WPA_G-0375; Indexed #297 (Item 2)
        - Note Regarding Sale Price of Bill of Sale Indenture, undated (Item 3)
        - Bill of Sale Indenture for Property in Chatham County, GA to Moses Sheftall [Oversized], April 4, 1807 (Item 4)
        - Note Regarding Item Added to Original Collection, Letter, Moses Sheftall to Haim Abendanone, undated (Item 5)
        - Moses Sheftall (Savannah, GA) to Haim Abendanone, December 28, 1815 S. Hammond, Columbia, SC Letter to Moses Sheftall, Savannah, December 19, 1827, December 28, 1815, December 19, 1827; WPA_H-0041; Indexed #307 (Item 6)
        - Federal Union, Milledgeville, Georgia [Oversized], June 20, 1833; WPA_G-0377; Indexed #308 (Item OS2)
        - Andrew McDowall & Co., Charleston, to Mr. I.A. Motta for Dr. Moses Sheftall, December 19, 1827 (Item 7)
        - Receipt for Forty-Four Yards of Kidderminster Carpeting, February 6, 1834; WPA_F-0468-A1; Indexed #309 (Item 8)
        - Snippet of Correspondence Possibly Regarding the Marriage of Dr. De la Motta's Sister; Notes that Raphel Mayer Married by the Hazan of the Congregation, Verso of F-0468-A, undated; WPA_F-0468-A; Indexed #309 (Item 9)
        - George Schley, P.M. [Postmaster], Savannah, to Dr. Moses Sheftall, receipt for .43¢ newspaper postage, June 1, 1834 - October 1, 1834; WPA_E-0202; Indexed #310 (Item 10)
    - Subseries III: Frances Sheftall, undated, 1788, 1802
      This subseries contains three items: one receipt from Frances Sheftall for payment of partial rent to William Hopton dated on March 10, 1778, and one draft letter draft petition regarding re-opening Mordecai Sheftall's claims against the United States. The draft letters are undated while the draft petition is dated March 15, 1802.
      - (Binder 1)
        - Frances Sheftall, Savannah, Drafts of Letters to Congressman John [Milledge] and to a United States Senator, Regarding Claim of Her Deceased Husband [Mordecai Sheftall], undated; WPA_G-0331; Indexed #327 (Item 1)
        - Invoice to Mary Hartley from Mrs. Sheftall for Sewing and Gowns, [Christmas Day], 1778 (Item 1A)
        - Receipt from Wm. Hopton to Mrs. Frances Sheftall for Partial Rent, March 10, 1778; WPA_B-0275; Indexed #262 (Item 2)
        - Widow Frances Sheftall Draft Petition to Congress, not signed, [March 15, 1802]; WPA_G-0233; Indexed #324 (Item 3)
    - Subseries IV: Benjamin Sheftall, undated, 1790, 1797